PASAN DISSANAYAKE

⊠ pasand@umd.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the area of responsible and trustworthy machine learning. I am particularly interested in using tools from information theory, statistics and optimization in explaining ML models and data, achieving privacy, and formulating the notions of fairness.

EDUCATION

University of Maryland, College Park, MD

Started Aug. 2022

PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering (CGPA: 4.0/4.0)

Adviser: Prof. Sanghamitra Dutta

Research focus: Responsible and trustworthy machine learning

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Graduated Aug. 2021

BSc (Hons.) in Electronic and Telecommunication Engineering (GPA: 4.04/4.2)

Research adviser: Dr. Prathapasinghe Dharmawansa

PUBLICATIONS

- P. Dissanayake and Sanghamitra Dutta, "The Role of Counterfactual Explanations in Model Extraction Attacks" (under review)
- P. Dissanayake, P. Dharmawansa and Y. Chen, "Distribution of the Scaled Condition Number of Single-Spiked Complex Wishart Matrices," in IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, vol. 68, no. 10, pp. 6716-6737, Oct. 2022
- P. Dharmawansa, **P. Dissanayake** and Y. Chen, "The Eigenvectors of Single-Spiked Complex Wishart Matrices: Finite and Asymptotic Analyses," in IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, vol. 68, no. 12, pp. 8092-8120, Dec. 2022

AWARDS AND HONORS

- Dean's Fellowship (2022) University of Maryland
- Dean's List (in all 8 semesters) University of Moratuwa
 For maintaining a semester GPA of 3.8 or higher during the considered semester
- Google Hash Code (2019) Country rank: 3
 Team programming competition based on real Google engineering problems
- MoraXtreme (2017) Second runners-up
 Team programming competition organized by IEEE Student Branch of University of Moratuwa

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Summer Research Assistant

May 2023 to Aug. 2023

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering,

University of Maryland, College Park, MD

Research focus: Risks of providing counterfactual explanations in terms of model extraction attacks (collaboration with Northrop Grumman)

Research Assistant

Aug. 2021 to Aug. 2022

Department of Electronic and Telecommunication Engineering,

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Research focus: Properties of single-spiked complex Wishart matrices

December, 2023 Page 1

EMPLOYMENT

Teaching Assistant

Aug. 2022 to Present

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering,

University of Maryland, College Park, MD

Lecturer (on Contract)

Dec. 2021 to Aug. 2022

Department of Electronic and Telecommunication Engineering,

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Systems Engineer (Intern)

Jun. 2019 to Dec. 2019

Infrastructure Solutions Team

MillenniumIT ESP (Pvt) Ltd., Colombo 07, Sri Lanka

Designed and implemented (in Proof of Concept level) a charging gateway for a leading telecom service provider, based on microservices architecture

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Maryland, College Park, MD

- ENEE420 Communication Systems (Fall 2022)
- ENEE324 Engineering Probability (Spring 2023, Fall 2023)
- ENEE436 Foundations of Machine Learning (Fall 2023)

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

- EN4720 Security in Cyber-Physical Systems
- EN2550 Fundamentals of Image Processing and Machine Vision
- EN3053 Digital Communications I

PRESENTATIONS

Model extraction using counterfactual explanations (Poster)

Northrop Grumman University Research Symposium, McLean, VA (Oct. 2023) North American School of Information Theory, Philadelphia, PA (June 2023)

COMPUTER LANGUAGES AND TOOLS

Programming: Python, C++, Java **Technical Computing:** MATLAB, Mathematica

Data/ML Frameworks: Tensorflow, PyTorch, Keras, Scikit-Learn, Pandas

CERTIFICATIONS

- Machine Learning Stanford University on Coursera
- Data Structures University of California, San Diego on Coursera
- Algorithmic Toolbox Offered by the University of California, San Diego on Coursera
- Certificate in Software Development in Java National Institute of Business Management, SL
- Networking Essentials (NE-CS3032-IN-16-EN) Offered by Cisco Networking Academy

RELEVANT COURSES

- CMSC742 Algorithms in Machine Learning: Guarantees and Analyses (UMD, Fall 2023)
- ENEE662 Convex Optimization (UMD, Fall 2023)
- ENEE621 Estimation and Detection Theory (UMD, Spring 2023, A+)
- ENEE627 Information Theory (UMD, Spring 2023, A)
- ENEE630 Advanced Digital Signal Processing (UMD, Fall 2022, A+)
- ENEE620 Random Processes in Communication and Control (UMD, Fall 2022, A)
- EN4573 Pattern Recognition and Machine Intelligence (UoM, Semester 8, A+)

December, 2023 Page 2

SERVICES AND OUTREACH

- Reviewer IEEE Wireless Communications Letters (view on Publons)
- Member of the panel of judges UMD Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (LSAMP) Fall Research Symposium 2023
- Mentor Montgomery Blair High School Magnet Student Program 2023
- Secretary Drama Society, University of Moratuwa for the year 2020/2021
- Co-chairperson Organizing committee of "Abhina 2019", the annual talent show of the Dept. of Electronic and Telecommunication Engineering
- Volunteer Soyuru Sathkaraya 2018: underprivileged school development project organized by Engineering Faculty Students' Union, University of Moratuwa
- Volunteer E-Care 2018: Underprivileged school development project organized by Electronics Club, Dept. of Electronic and Telecommunication, University of Moratuwa
- Volunteer Grama Prabodhaya 2017: Underprivileged school development project and junior high school seminar series organized by Rotaract Club, University of Moratuwa

December, 2023 Page 3